Jorge Barata November 1, 1987

BSc. in Computer Engineering, MSc. in Distributed Systems

Madrid, Spain

+34 619 98 15 38
contact@jorgebg.com
github.com/jorgebg
in linkedin.com/in/baratajorge
jorgebg.com

Summary

Senior Software Engineer, specialized in **software engineering** mainly with *Django*, *SQL*, *React*, and *AWS*. Experience in **reliability** following *SRE* principles, **machine learning** with *Scipy* and *scikit-learn*, and **big** data with *Spark*.

Strong **software design** skills, looking forward to developing a career as **Software Architect**, having gathered extensive knowledge in integrating a broad range of state-of-the-art patterns and technologies.

Active free and open-source software contributor and speaker.

EXPERIENCE

Please refer to his Linked-in profile to see the recommendations.

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

September 2018 - December 2022 • Eventbrite, Madrid

Eventbrite is the market leader for live event ticketing globally. The platform handles hundreds of thousands of requests during the on-sales.

Worked in a fast paced agile environment with distributed teams in different locations and time zones.

Leaded the following projects:

- Migration of a Django+PySOA service to a Kotlin+gRPC service. Zero downtime using traffic shadowing and incremental rollout. This resolved existing performance bottlenecks and streamlined the communication across the services in our SOA model.
- Migration of a Redis-backed Django service to ElastiCache, reducing operational overhead and enhancing reliability and scalability.
- Migration of parts of the monolith to SOA services in Django+PySOA, facilitating independent development and scalability.
- Django training for the teams in Spain, empowering engineers with expertise and improving the onboarding, as most of our services were built in Django.

Added new features to the event listing page and ticket order page, which improved the sales funnel.

Joined the SRE team for some time, where I worked on the following projects:

- Migration from in-house infrastructure management system to Terraform and CloudFormation, enabling efficient provisioning and consistent configurations across environments.
- Helped the teams to set up Datadog dashboards, monitoring alerts, SLAs and error budgets, which allowed them
 to measure performance and improve the reliability.

Conducted over a hundred interviews and delivered many talks in tech events, playing a pivotal role in talent acquisition and knowledge dissemination, enriching our team with diverse talents and fostering industry connections.

Founded and organized the Django Madrid User Group, and Eventbrite sponsored the meetups. This brought more candidates to the hiring pipeline.

Stack:

- Backend: Django, Django REST Framework, Celery, MySQL, Redis, Elastic Search, PySOA, RabbitMQ, Kafka.
- Frontend: React, TypeScript.
- Infrastructure: Docker, uWSGI, HashiCorp (Consul, Nomad, Terraform), AWS (Fargate, DynamoDB, Elasti-Cache, CloudFormation), NGINX, HAProxy, Ubuntu, GitHub, Datadog, Sentry.

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

July 2015 - August 2018 • Udemy, Dublin

Udemy for Business (UFB) team. We created a platform with 20k+ courses offering on-demand, immersive, and cohort-based learning for businesses.

Worked in a fast paced agile environment with distributed teams in different locations and time zones.

Leaded the following projects:

- Hierarchical taxonomy management system for the course collection. It allowed the customers to organize the courses and increased adoption.
- Refactoring of the UFB's search system, moving from a dedicated implementation to a shared solution for the
 whole organization, which improved the team speed for developing experiments, new features, and the adoption
 from external developments.
- Enriched the course search by adding related lectures, which resulted on more search clicks and course consumption
- A RESTful public API, enabling customers integration to the platform.
- Instrumentalization to monitor the quality of the delivery, alarms that notified the team on fortuitous behaviours.

Developed a self-service system that allowed customers to create learning portals for small teams. This helped to acommodate a market that today represents an important share of the current business.

Migrated old code to new stacks:

- From a in-house PHP framework to Django. This improved the onboarding learning curve.
- From Angular 1 to React+MobX, which gave us more flexibility.

Developed data pipelines for UFB analytics in Amazon Redshift, Pinball, Python and ChartIO.

3rd party services integration: Intercom, Slack, Marketo, PingOne/PingFederate.

Stack:

- Backend: Django, Django Rest Framework, Celery, MySQL, Memcached, Redis, Elastic Search.
- Frontend: React, MobX, Webpack, Babel, Karma.
- Infrastructure: Docker, uWSGI, Fabric, Ansible, CentOS, GitHub, Jenkins, Datadog.

② udemy.com ② business.udemy.com

CO-FOUNDER & CTO

November 2016 – $today \circ Cooperativa Social Los Mochuelos$, Madrid

Lead the development and launch of the *Reutiliza* project, a place for exchange and reuse of items. Built in Django and PostgreSQL. Deployed on Debian with uWSGI, Nginx and Ansible.

Technology advisor for the different activities of the cooperative, as well as system management and software development. Wordpress multi-site, infrastructure, networking, and office suite.

O mochuelos.com O reutilizabocema.com

Co-founder & CTO

June 2014 - November 2014 • Indievelopment, Dublin

Co-founder of a LaunchBox 2015 startup (Trinity College's accelerator for student startups).

Designed the software architecture for deployment on Microsoft Azure.

Requirements-gathering through interviews, web forms and social networks.

❷ indievelopment.info ❷ launchbox.ie/companies/indievelopment ❷ www.f6s.com/indievelopment

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

September 2012 – June 2014 。 $Vivocom\ EU,\ Spain$

Extended the web application architecture (Yii+MySQL) with MongoDB, caching, background workers and querying, automation tools (Grunt), TTD, code quality linter, web security pentesting. Leaded the frontend implementation with CoffeeScript, CommonJS and Bower. Also trained the team for those new technologies/paradigms.

Software design with ArgoUML, Continuous Integration with Github, Agile development with Kanban/Scrum/Redmine Server side performance optimization with PHPcache. Database query optimization of MySQL/MongoDB.

Built a real time chat for the website: Integrated an Ejjaberd chat server with a WSDL DaaS. Web client built in Ember.js.

100,000 registered users in its first year. Funded by the Spanish Ministry of Industry, Energy and Tourism as part of *Plan Avanza 2* program. It was awarded the Prize for Most innovative business project by the *Inspirational Festival* of 2013.

References: Raúl Fernández Fraile 🕲 linkedin.com/in/rfraile, Kublai Gómez Soto 🕲 linkedin.com/in/kublai

♦ keepunto.com
♦ youtu.be/usjou9iFj7U
♦ planavanza.es
♦ inspirationalfestival.com

JUNIORIOS SOFTWARED DINCINEER

Migrated the old application to Yii Framework, and trained the team on this new framework.

Analyst programmer and Web Developer, mainly with PHP/MySQL stack and JavaScript. Also helping as systems technician with Apache, Ubuntu and Amazon EC2.

Optimized the most heavy database queries, and the web client with PageSpeed and CloudFlare. Also improved the display algorithm that placed user-published photos, videos and texts into an horizontal wall.

Max peak reached with 12,500 unique visitors in one day.

Agile Development with Redmine and continuous integration with GitHub.

Reference: Raúl Fernández Fraile 🔾 linkedin.com/in/rfraile

♦ koowall.com ♦ vimeo.com/37125476

SOFTWARE ANALYST & DEVELOPER

June 2009 - April 2011 o InDaHouseRulez, Spain

Developing frontends, customer facing and backend features, multilingual websites with advertising revenues.

Django, Symfony, Yii, Wordpress, MySQL. Also helped as systems technician with web servers (Cherokee, Apache), mail server (Postfix) and Debian/BSD.

Agile Development with ActiveCollab, continuous integration with SVN

Recommendation: @linkedin.com/in/baratajorge/en#recommendations

Reference: Rubén Hernández 🔾 linkedin.com/in/rubenhernandeza

② indahouserulez.com ③ usitility.com ② regalomascotas.com ③ quevicio.com

Computer Technician

September 2008 – June 2009 • Carlos III University of Madrid, Spain

Customer Service Center, technical support of the university, providing assistance to both staff and students. Computer maintenance (hardware and software), printers, networks, etc.

EDUCATION

B.Sc. Computer Engineering, M.Sc Distributed Systems august 2007 – August 2017 \circ Carlos III University of Madrid, Spain

Taxi Recommendation System for Big Data: Final dissertation. It consisted of two parts:

- Data pipeline built in SciPy, scikit-learn, and Spark and deployed in the laboratory cluster.
- Web application with geospatial features built in Django and PostGIS.

♀ github.com/jorgebg/taxi-recommendation-system

M.Sc Teacher Training August 2023 – July 2024 • Universidad Europea, Spain

Languages

Spanish: native

English: fluent (4 years working in Ireland, C1)

COMMUNITY

Formar founder and organizer of Madrid Django User Group. @www.meetup.com/MadridDjango/

Former founder and organizer of **Dublin Django User Group**. @ www.meetup.com/django-dublin/

Contributed to OSS projects: **Django**, **Yii**, **Symfony**, along others.